And that's how actually we discovered that we need to change the world's focus from schooling to learning, from just counting how many bodies are in classrooms to actually how many are learning. And the second big task was, can we do anything about this? Can we do anything about this big, vast, silent, maybe most-neglected international crisis? And what we found out is, we can. It's actually amazing.
De ese modo descubrimos que necesitamos cambiar el enfoque mundial de la escolarización al aprendizaje, de solo contar cuántos cuerpos hay en las aulas a contar cuántos están aprendiendo. Y la segunda gran tarea fue, ¿podemos hacer algo al respecto? ¿Podemos hacer algo con esta gran crisis mundial tan vasta y silenciosa, y quizá en gran parte desatendida? Y descubrimos que sí, podemos hacer algo. En realidad es increíble.
We can, for the first time, have every child in school and learning within just one generation. And we don't even have to really invent the wheel to do so. We just need to learn from the best in class, but not any best in class -- the best in your own class. What we did is actually we looked at countries by income level: low-income, mid-income, high-income. We looked at what the 25 percent fastest improvers in education do, and what we found out is that if every country moves at the same rate as the fastest improvers within their own income level, then within just one generation we can have every child in school and learning. Let me give you an example.
Por primera vez podemos tener a todos los niños en la escuela aprendiendo en solo una generación. Y no tenemos que reinventar la rueda para lograrlo. Solo tenemos que aprender de los mejores en su clase, pero no el mejor de cualquier clase, el mejor en tu propia clase. Analizamos los países por nivel de ingresos: bajos ingresos, ingresos medios, altos ingresos. Observamos el 25 % de los factores que más aceleran la mejora educativa, y descubrimos que si cada país se mueve al ritmo de los factores más dinámicos dentro de su propio nivel de ingresos, entonces dentro de una sola generación podemos tener a todos los niños en la escuela aprendiendo. Les daré un ejemplo.
Let's take Tunisia for example. We're not telling Tunisia, "You should move as fast as Finland." No disrespect, Finland. We're telling Tunisia, "Look at Vietnam." They spend similar amounts for primary and secondary pupils as percentage of GDP per capita, but achieves today higher results. Vietnam introduced a standardized assessment for literacy and numeracy, teachers in Vietnam are better monitored than in other developing countries, and students' achievements are made public. And it shows in the results. In the 2015 PISA -- Program for International Student Assessment -- Vietnam outperformed many wealthy economies, including the United States. Now, if you're not an education expert, you may ask, "What's new and different? Don't all countries track student progress and make those achievements public?" No. The sad answer is no.
Tomemos a Túnez, por ejemplo. No le estamos diciendo a Túnez: "Debes moverte tan rápido como Finlandia". Sin ánimo de ofender, Finlandia. Le estamos diciendo a Túnez, "Mira a Vietnam". Gasta cantidades similares para alumnos de primaria y secundaria respecto al porcentaje del PIB per cápita, pero logra resultados más altos. Vietnam introdujo una evaluación de alfabetización y aritmética, se controla mejor a los docentes que en otros países en desarrollo, y los logros de los estudiantes se hacen públicos. Y eso se ve en los resultados. En el informe PISA 2015 -- Programa de Evaluación Internacional de Estudiantes -- Vietnam superó a muchas economías ricas, incluyendo a Estados Unidos. Ahora, si uno no es un experto en educación, podría preguntarse: "¿Qué hay de nuevo y diferente? ¿No registran todos los países el progreso de los estudiantes y publican sus logros?" No. La triste respuesta es que no.
We are very far from it. Only half of the developing countries have systematic learning assessment at primary school, and even less so at lower secondary school. So if we don't know if children are learning, how are teachers supposed to focus their attention on delivering results, and how are countries supposed to prioritize education spending actually to delivering results, if they don't know if children are learning? That's why the first big transformation before investing is to make the education system deliver results. Because pouring more money into broken systems may only fund more inefficiencies. And what deeply worries me -- if children go to school and don't learn, it devalues education, and it devalues spending on education, so that governments and political parties can say,
Estamos muy lejos de eso. Solo la mitad de los países en desarrollo hacen evaluación sistemática del aprendizaje en primaria, y aún menos en los primeros años de la escuela secundaria. Entonces, si no sabemos si los niños aprenden, ¿cómo harán los maestros para centrar su atención en conseguir resultados, y cómo se supone que los países priorizarán el gasto en educación para conseguir resultados, si no saben si los niños aprenden? Por eso la primera gran transformación antes de invertir es hacer que el sistema educativo entregue resultados. Porque poner más dinero en sistemas rotos solo financiará más ineficiencias. Y lo que me preocupa profundamente... si los niños van a la escuela y no aprenden, eso devalúa la educación y devalúa el gasto en educación, de forma que gobiernos y partidos políticos puedan decir:
"Oh, we are spending so much money on education, but children are not learning. They don't have the right skills. Maybe we should spend less." Now, improving current education systems to deliver results is important, but won't be enough.
"Estamos gastando mucho dinero en educación, pero los niños no aprenden. No tienen las habilidades correctas. Quizá deberíamos gastar menos". Mejorar los sistemas educativos actuales para obtener resultados es importante, pero no será suficiente. ¿Qué pasa en países que no tengan suficientes profesores cualificados? Por ejemplo, Somalia. Si cada estudiante somalí se hiciera maestro -- si cada persona con estudios universitarios se hiciera maestro -- no tendríamos suficientes maestros. ¿Y qué hay de los niños que están en campos de refugiados, o en zonas rurales muy remotas? Tomemos a Filipe como ejemplo. Filipe vive en una de las miles de comunidades a la vera del río Amazonas. Su pueblo de 78 personas tiene 20 familias. Filipe y un compañero de estudios eran los únicos dos en bachillerato en 2015. Amazonas es un estado del noroeste brasileño. Es cuatro veces y media más grande que Alemania, y está completamente cubierto de jungla y ríos. Hace una década, Filipe y su compañero habrían tenido solo dos alternativas:
moving to Manaus, the capital, or stopping studying altogether, which most of them did. In 2009, however, Brazil passed a new law that made secondary education a guarantee for every Brazilian and an obligation for every state to implement this by 2016. But giving access to high-quality education, you know, in the Amazonas state, is huge and expensive. How are you going to get, you know, math and science and history teachers all over those communities? And even if you find them, many of them would not want to move there. So faced with this impossible task,
mudarse a Manaos, la capital, o dejar de estudiar por completo, algo que la mayoría hizo. En 2009, sin embargo, Brasil aprobó una nueva ley que garantizó la educación secundaria para cada brasileño y la obligación para cada estado de implementarla antes de 2016. Pero dar acceso a una educación de alta calidad, en el estado de Amazonas, es una tarea enorme y costosa. ¿Cómo conseguir profesores de matemáticas, ciencia e historia en todas esas comunidades? E incluso si los encuentras, muchos de ellos no querrían mudarse allí. Así que frente a esta tarea imposible,
civil servants and state officials developed amazing creativity and entrepreneurship. They developed the media center solution. It works this way. You have specialized, trained content teachers in Manaus delivering classroom via livestream to over a thousand classrooms in those scattered communities. Those classrooms have five to 25 students, and they're supported by a more generalist tutoring teacher for their learning and development. The 60 content teachers in Manaus work with over 2,200 tutoring teachers in those communities to customize lesson plans to the context and time. Now, why is this division between content teacher and tutoring teacher important? First of all, as I told you, because in many countries, we just don't have enough qualified teachers. But secondly also because teachers do too many things they're either not trained for or not supposed to do. Let's look at Chile, for example. In Chile, for every doctor, you have four and a half people, four and a half staff supporting them, and Chile is on the low end of the spectrum here, because in developing countries, on average, every doctor has 10 people supporting them. A teacher in Chile, however, has less than half a person, 0.3 persons, supporting them. Imagine a hospital ward with 20, 40, 70 patients and you have a doctor doing it all by themselves: no nurses, no medical assistants, no one else. You will say this is absurd and impossible, but this is what teachers are doing all over the world every day with classrooms of 20, 40, or 70 students. So this division between content and tutoring teachers is amazing because it is changing the paradigm of the teacher,
funcionarios y representantes del estado desarrollaron una increíble creatividad y espíritu emprendedor. Desarrollaron la solución del centro de medios. Funciona de esta manera. Hay maestros de contenido especializado en Manaos que dan clases de manera virtual a más de mil aulas en esas comunidades dispersas. Esas aulas tienen de 5 a 25 estudiantes, y cuentan con el apoyo de un profesor de tutoría más generalista para su aprendizaje y desarrollo. Los 60 profesores de contenido en Manaos trabajan con más de 2200 profesores de tutoría en esas comunidades para personalizar sus clases al contexto y el tiempo. Ahora, ¿por qué es importante esta división entre maestro y maestro de tutoría? Antes que nada, como dije, porque en muchos países, simplemente no tenemos suficientes maestros cualificados. Pero también porque los maestros hacen demasiadas cosas para las que no fueron capacitados o se supone que no deberían hacer. Miremos a Chile, por ejemplo. En Chile, por cada médico, hay cuatro personas y media, cuatro personas y media de apoyo, y Chile está en el extremo inferior del espectro aquí, porque en los países en desarrollo, de media, cada médico tiene 10 personas de apoyo. Un profesor en Chile, sin embargo, tiene menos de media persona, 0,3 personas, de apoyo. Imaginen una sala de hospital con 20, 40, 70 pacientes y un médico que hace todo por sí mismo: sin enfermeros, sin ayudantes médicos, nadie más. Dirán que esto es absurdo e imposible, pero es la realidad cotidiana de los maestros en el mundo con aulas de 20, 40 o 70 estudiantes. Entonces esta división entre maestros de contenidos y tutoría es increíble porque está cambiando el paradigma del maestro,
so that each does what they can do best and so that children are not just in school but in school and learning. And some of these content teachers, they became celebrity teachers. You know, some of them run for office, and they helped raise the status of the profession so that more students wanted to become teachers. And what I love about this example is beyond changing the paradigm of the teacher. It teaches us how we can harness technology for learning. The live-streaming is bidirectional, so students like Filipe and others can present information back. And we know technology is not always perfect. You know, state officials expect between five to 15 percent of the classrooms every day to be off live-stream because of flood, broken antennas or internet not working. And yet, Filipe is one of over 300,000 students that benefited from the media center solution and got access to postprimary education. This is a living example how technology is not just an add-on but can be central to learning and can help us bring school to children if we cannot bring children to school. Now, I hear you. You're going to say, "How are we going to implement this all over the world?" I've been in government myself and have seen how difficult it is even to implement the best ideas. So as a commission, we started two initiatives to make the "Learning Generation" a reality. The first one is called the Pioneer Country Initiative. Over 20 countries from Africa and Asia have committed to make education their priority and to transform their education systems to deliver results. We've trained country leaders in a methodology called the delivery approach. What this does is basically two things. In the planning phase, we take everyone into a room -- teachers, teacher unions, parent associations, government officials, NGOs, everyone -- so that the reform and the solution we come up with are shared by everyone and supported by everyone. And in the second phase, it does something special. It's kind of a ruthless focus on follow-up. So week by week you check, has that been done, what was supposed to be done, and even sometimes sending a person physically to the district or school to check that versus just hoping that it happened. It may sound for many common sense, but it's not common practice, and that's why actually many reforms fail. It has been piloted in Tanzania, and there the pass rate for students in secondary education was increased by 50 percent in just over two years. Now, the next initiative to make the Learning Generation a reality is financing. Who's going to pay for this? So we believe and argue that domestic financing has to be the backbone of education investment. Do you remember when I told you about Vietnam earlier outperforming the United States in PISA? That's due to a better education system, but also to Vietnam increasing their investment
para que cada uno haga lo que mejor puede hacer para que los niños no solo estén en la escuela sino en la escuela aprendiendo. Y algunos de estos maestros de contenido, se hicieron famosos. Algunos se postularon para un cargo, y ayudaron a mejorar el estatus de la profesión para que más estudiantes quisieran ser maestros. Y de este ejemplo me encanta que va más allá de cambiar el paradigma del maestro. Nos enseña a aprovechar la tecnología para el aprendizaje. La transmisión en vivo es bidireccional, es decir, Filipe y los otros pueden enviar información de regreso. Y sabemos que la tecnología no siempre es perfecta. Los funcionarios esperan que entre el 5 y el 15 % de las aulas estén sin conexión cada día debido a inundaciones, antenas rotas o Internet que no funciona. Y, sin embargo, Filipe es uno de más de 300 000 estudiantes que se benefició del centro de medios y tuvo acceso a la educación postprimaria. Este es un ejemplo viviente de que la tecnología no es solo un complemento sino una pieza clave para el aprendizaje y puede acercar la escuela a los niños, si no podemos acercar los niños a la escuela. Ahora, los escucho. Van a decir: "¿Cómo vamos a implementar esto en todo el mundo?" Yo misma he estado en el gobierno y he visto lo difícil que es incluso implementar las mejores ideas. Entonces, como comisión, comenzamos dos iniciativas para hacer de la generación del aprendizaje una realidad. La primera se llama Iniciativa de País Pionero. Más de 20 países de África y Asia se han comprometido a hacer de la educación su prioridad y a transformar sus sistemas educativos para entregar resultados. Hemos entrenado a líderes en cada país en una metodología llamada enfoque a la entrega. Esto persigue dos objetivos. En la fase de planificación, llevamos a todos a una sala: maestros, sindicatos de docentes, asociaciones de padres, representantes del gobierno, ONGs, a todos... para que la reforma y la solución que se nos ocurra sean compartidas por todos y cuenten con el apoyo de todos. Y la segunda fase, es un tanto especial. Es una especie de enfoque despiadado en el seguimiento. Semana a semana, uno verifica si se hizo lo que debía hacerse, incluso a veces se envía a una persona físicamente al distrito o la escuela para verificar que ocurrió en vez de esperar que suceda. Puede que para muchos suene a sentido común, pero no es una práctica común, y por eso muchas reformas fallan. Ha sido probado en Tanzania, y allí la tasa de aprobados de los estudiantes de educación secundaria se incrementó en un 50 % en poco más de dos años. La próxima iniciativa para hacer de la generación del aprendizaje una realidad es la financiación, quién pagará esto. Creemos y argumentamos que la financiación interna debe ser la columna vertebral de la inversión. ¿Recuerdan cuando antes les hablé sobre Vietnam que superó a EE.UU. en PISA? Eso se debe a un mejor sistema educativo, pero también a que Vietnam ha aumentado su inversión
from seven to 20 percent of their national budget in two decades. But what happens if countries want to borrow money for education? If you wanted to borrow money to build a bridge or a road, it's quite easy and straightforward, but not for education. It's easier to make a shiny picture of a bridge and show it to everyone than one of an educated mind. That's kind of a longer term commitment. So we came up with a solution to help countries escape the middle income trap, countries that are not poor enough or not poor, thankfully, anymore, that cannot profit from grants or interest-free loans, and they're not rich enough to be able to have attractive interests on their loans. So we're pooling donor money in a finance facility for education, which will provide more finance for education. We will subsidize, or even eliminate completely, interest payments on the loans so that countries that commit to reforms can borrow money, reform their education system, and pay this money over time
de un 7 a un 20 % de su presupuesto nacional en dos décadas.
while benefiting from a better-educated population.
mientras se benefician de una población mejor educada.
This solution has been recognized in the last G20 meeting in Germany, and so finally today education is on the international agenda. But let me bring this back to the personal level, because this is where the impact lands. Without that decision to invest a young country's budget, 20 percent of a young country's budget in education, I would have never been able to go to school, let alone in 2014 becoming a minister in the government that successfully ended the transition phase. Tunisia's Nobel Peace Prize in 2015 as the only democracy that emerged from the Arab Spring is a legacy to that bold leadership decision. Education is the civil rights struggle, it's the human rights struggle of our generation. Quality education for all: that's the freedom fight that we've got to win. Thank you. (Applause)
Esta solución ha sido reconocida en la última reunión del G20 en Alemania, y finalmente hoy la educación está en la agenda internacional. Pero permítanme llevar esto nuevamente al plano personal, porque aquí es donde yace el impacto. Sin esa decisión de invertir el presupuesto de un país joven, 20 % del presupuesto de un país joven en educación, yo nunca podría haber ido a la escuela, y mucho menos en 2014 convertirme en ministra en el gobierno que terminó exitosamente la fase de transición. El Premio Nobel de la Paz de Túnez en 2015 como la única democracia que surgió de la Primavera Árabe es un legado de esa decisión audaz de liderazgo. La educación es la lucha por los derechos civiles, es la lucha por los derechos humanos de nuestra generación. Educación de calidad para todos: esa es la lucha por la libertad que tenemos que ganar. Gracias. (Aplausos)